on all right and I start forgot to ask
how to pronounce your name Zahara you
got it Yahaira hi I have to have okay
and David welcome to the idea cafe today
we are discussing the question what are
your thoughts and feelings on communism
or Marxism and we generally each take up
to five minutes you're also welcome to
pass if at the end after everyone has
spoken you don't want to speak you can
say that you don't want to have a turn
to share for the five minutes
uninterrupted and in that case you can
still be part of the discussion
discussion at the end so if either of
you would like to go first or I'm also
open to going first
uncle s start and I'll know I think I
can be brief because I actually haven't
read Marx I haven't studied communism I
mean other than just the general
awareness but my so my perspective is I
was I was impacted most by watching
people debate it you know the the sense
of you don't really understand what it
is you're you're using the historical
what what has happened with communism as
a as a critique of Marx and people say
you know there's a lot of ideas and
marks that don't get aired I am sure
that that's true I'm sure that there's a
lot there that is worth looking into and
that's the piece that I'd really like to
understand for people to be able to
bring that forward what are the things
that would be worth considering I know
that some of the criticism is the way
that Marx is presented is through the
through the historical impact you know
that communism has been has been
terrible and it's and it has been
attempted to be implemented in a period
of time when we had when the Industrial
Revolution was brand-new we're just
learning new social technologies
so there is a lot that is like how
possible would it be to even implement
ideas of better ideals you know how do
how do we make things better for the
world I said there's a lot that I think
is worthwhile if we can really move past
a sense of everything was good back then
or you know that that marks is stated in
a way that if we could just implement it
purely then we would see something I my
my own sense I'll say this and this
isn't really so much communism or
Marxism specifically but my idea is that
our desire for utopia I actually
exploring my own desire for utopia I see
a fallacy and that I see that I have a
vision for something wonderful that
could happen if only other people's
selfishness didn't interfere with my
beneficence it's like hmm
I think I'm looking at this from a
particular lens that is only seeing my
my positive attributes and everyone else
is negative attributes and trying to
balance it in that way rather than
really recognizing how do I also face
the challenge of overcoming my shadows
and help why's everyone up to be their
best Ellison and and overcome their
shadows in a way that they would want to
so I think that that I think is the
essence of what is difficult to achieve
by when I when I think of achieving
utopia yeah that actually it's it's
somewhat embodied in the rule Omega as
well as I'm engaged in rule awake I'm
realizing I'm doing that I'm actually
noticing where am I not giving the best
benefit of the doubt where am I not
actually meeting the person and then
it's said interacting with the idea
other person the same thing is true with
utopia where am i dealing with the idea
in my head about what's being
rather than actually and encountering
the actual world actual people actually
my actual self in this moment and it
seems that that in the discussion that I
saw a flare up that was the case it
seemed like a more so we were dealing
with the idea at it rather than the
actuality I'll pause there all right
thank you David do you still want me to
go first actually so I think that was
beautifully said I agree I'm somewhere
in those lines as well I do not know
much about Marxism communism except what
I've learned in school what we know from
history from reading and I think that I
tend to do the same thing and a lot of
people tend to do the same thing as is
sort of like judge it based on
historical events I I believe that it
has a lot of good in it but in the same
train as David I would say that it's
also it has a lot of barriers and
challenges because it's the Stila system
it's so system so I I value freedom
that's one of my values I see that it's
a system that doesn't give much way to
freedom
freedom of speech freedom of of being
innovative creating you know having
creating your own having your own
resources and creating your own you know
restaurant or whatever it may be so in
that sense I I think that it could be
something that can be used but not fully
I think that we can draw a lot of
positivity from it you can draw certain
concepts from it but I think that we may
also need to add to it in order for it
to work in a way that it will work in
creating
utopia if that's possible yeah that's my
lease on it so far I have a lot of views
on it but so far that's like the surface
for me I do not know much about it I
know a little bit about it I'm
fascinated by the same with the debates
and people discussing it and their
points of view and I'm I can't say that
I am against it or for it I just think
that is in itself it's flawed and I
think that it may need to be maybe
tweaked a little bit or expanded upon or
something like that alright thank you
and I will take a turn since there's
only three of us
my similar to both of you I think there
is a lot of amazing qualities in Marxism
and communism as it is written out in
its purest form the fact that we can
come together and work for the for the
group and overcome our selfishness and
find a path that's best for everyone and
living towards this like common utopia I
also think when it's been implemented in
the real world whether the letter of the
law or not human nature gets in the way
we take on power and we don't want to
give it back we want people we want to
control people and force them to be
selfless force them to work for the
greater the greater part of the group
and in doing so take away the beauty
that is there take away the individual
beauty and the beauty of the collective
like that we don't get the innovation we
don't get when we don't have personal
freedom when someone else is dictating
what your life should look like and what
goods and you should be doing and what
your your profession should be you're
not able to tap into your flow in your
genius and do what you're here to do
when it's been implemented there has
been mass murder and genocide and if
that needs to be your tool to get people
to fall in line it's clearly a bad tool
and so finding the pieces that work the
pieces we want to try and always owning
whatever
we're going to put into place can go
wrong and how do we fix it when it goes
wrong how do we how do we think about it
before it it before we implement
something what could go wrong and how do
we kind of negate for that and then at
the same time always being open to yes
and I think that's also one of the big
problems of communism was that they
would set quotas and there was
incentives to lie there was incentives
to fudge the data because you would be
punished if you didn't and to look at
incentives and say but what happens when
this when someone meets it and when
someone doesn't if we can allow people
to be truly honest about what the data
is that is I think the greatest way that
we can help the commons to you know that
it's not okay well we made 80 bushels of
grain it's like did you actually grow 80
bushels of grain and if you didn't why
like was it a labor brought like was it
a labor problem was it a actual like the
soil didn't grow that much the the
temperature whatever it happens to be
that if the information is true and
accurate we can get a better yield next
time as opposed to just making somebody
wrong and shipping them off to prison
because they didn't happen to make a
quota that isn't possibly even even able
to be made so I think within the space
of of game B what how I'm playing game
be how I want how I envision the world
to towards this proto PIA that we never
quite reach is that everyone has their
own individual freedom
no one's dictating what you get to do
and we have these autonomous groups that
work together and there's an efficiency
in the global system that doesn't
infringe on those two things it only
supports them it supports the the
individual freedom and the group
autonomy that we want to be part of and
I will also end that here so we can have
a open discussion I'm meeting both of
you
there you go we all shared within eleven
minutes so we have up to the half an
hour mark to have an open discussion if
we would like to
I love what you said about being able to
be honest about you know like you said
the quotas and not only that but um I
was reading a little bit about it and I
was reading and I have a friend actually
that she is from Poland so not too long
ago they they had a communist country
and she was telling me how they used to
go into the markets and you know know
that they would be shortage of food so
they would be trading in this black
market because they didn't have enough
light of a certain resource so it would
create a black market which I actually
read that it creates a black market
which in turn then what it does it um
people start losing the trust in the
people that are planning this economy
which in turn it's like a vicious cycle
because then it will turn into
capitalism again so is is if it's like
we're going in circles in a way you know
if we were to go through blue cap you
know come in Assam so I think in is
integrity is is you know raising people
to that level of accountability and
integrity you know in order for
something like this to be sustained
because they were required like a very
high standard level of integrity so yeah
I'd like it is there's there
that reminds me one of the part of where
my information comes from her might were
my innocent form from my father spent
some time in Poland and Russia and then
China starting in the nineties as a
consultant working in the United States
as a businessman Poland originally said
hey we're looking at turning it into an
economy how do we how do we do that what
would be the considerations how do you
know we don't have any idea we've not
been trained in that and so his his
exposure was people who wanted to become
more capitalist to really understand how
to invest capital to grow
and the mindset shift between what they
thought and what they need no it was
just so the perception so my father's
opinion before he went was basically
coming as in the capsules is the same
people are the same it's a very simple
thing between them when he got over
there like other the mines it's such a
different mindset it's difficult to
actually understand the two worlds
from one perspective I don't think any
but you know it really changed his mind
not from the perspective of saying that
communism was bad but it was just like
it was so different I don't think we
give it a full consideration of what's
there but but I also think that that
this notion of how do we get to the best
version of ourselves there's there's a
part of this that I think is a really
challenging part I think that we're born
effectively in a larval stage of
humanity I think that human beings have
to grow up to a certain point before we
can really fully give the varsity's so a
lot of what you are saying Jubilee about
how do we not be how do we not be
selfish how do we how do we make sure
that we get what we need in order to
grow fully in order to be able to
contribute fully what I would say is I
think that there are two part of that
one is that a basic minimum for the
essential needs and then the other part
is how do we have a feedback mechanism
that says how well or what is how what
impact are your actions having on
yourself and the people around you and
one of the things that I think is
interesting at this moment in time is
things like with blockchain in the
internet and and artificial intelligence
and different ways that we can not only
monitor and see but analyze and share
and perspectives on the feedback loops
that we have are very different than
it's ever been in the past so I think
there's an incredible opportunity to do
things as well as all sorts of ways in
which this can go badly as well so I
think the kinds of considerations for
either capitalism or communism are so
different that it really takes
a fresh start of how do we I mean what
what do we want to accomplish how do we
take these feedback and mechanisms into
account so I'll pause there yeah I think
that's um accurate I think that we live
in a time period due to technology and
our globalization that we've never been
able to implement a system that we're
now capable of implementing we really I
think as a species we really suck at
central planning because we never have
perfect knowledge even if you have every
piece of knowledge that the three of us
have there's going to be a lot of
information we don't have and so you
plan based on your best information and
if you're not happy if you're not
allowing feedback into the system you're
missing out and that's where the idea of
incentives right if you're going to be
punished for not having perfect
information you're gonna pretend you
have perfect information you're gonna
you know you're gonna you're gonna have
blind spots to to what isn't isn't
happening if everyone can say what isn't
working what they think won't work what
they what they can see is not working
for them as an individual and have a say
and how to improve it for themselves
with groups that also have those same
issues I think there's a lot of power we
can have as individuals and as small
groups that is what I am working on
creating in the world is the ability to
to do that with technology that we all
own together in a cooperative so can I
can I say something
just support that is also the stigma
that communism has in the whole world as
well and I that's why I hate labels
because if there was something else that
we can cut you call it you know a
different type of system because I think
within the stigma itself it would create
a lot of problems with people that are
not fully grasping what it would mean or
the the different you know how it would
be different that how it would be
different then it was in the past or in
history and I think that
it will create the opposite of what we
will be trying to create utopia because
then you have sections of group 1 group
understanding what is trying to be
implemented and then the other group not
really understanding and then going by
the stigma of what communism our system
yes so if it's possible and not possible
I think it's maybe I'm wrong but I think
that maybe creating a new system that
wouldn't be label communists or mrsa
cyst or any of that it's just a new
system that is implementing implementing
concepts that work that work for
everyone you know it's just a little
thought pause so I like that there's
there's a nuance here that I said I
really want to think about because in a
way we're critiquing Marxism and
communism from the historical impact and
and the people who are proponents of
Marx say well Marx that's totally be
given a chance it's not it's not pure
but you could say the same thing is true
for capitalism capitalism isn't really
given a full chance and in a way neither
of those in their pew forum probably
works the thought that comes to mind for
me is I'm pretty I have a bias that this
is fact but I have a pretty fun bias
that heavy feedback loop or systems of
feedback loops are going to be very
essential for whatever works we're gonna
actually have to be able to be
transparent about what is the actual
impact that works for everyone who was
everyone what does work mean how are
they outliers
how many of those are there had how far
outside of outliers out there you know
or do they have an opportunity to come
back in we're really being honest about
what the impact is and what's happening
in that one of the things that I'm
seeing more of and this is something
that I became very very clear to me is
that and the and the current rhetoric
around what
an income disparity or wealth
distribution it's getting worse and
worse right and in some sense there's a
view that oh well this is just this is
just greed there's another view that
it's it actually is a free-market
economy
makes the rich richer it is inherently
not only designed that way but it's it's
a it's energetically works that way and
so if you don't have checks and bounces
or some way to to cause the flow to get
the other direction it will go towards
that towards wealth inequality the rich
will continue to get richer so there has
to be a mechanism for for doing
something in the other direction well
I'm really curious about things like
what Bernie Sanders wants it how do we
inject capital or inject resources back
down to the roots to the individuals out
there so that they had a capacity to
continue to grow up and I else a little
bit the idea that debt Jubilee or the
idea of really doing something to make
sure that people real 'evil the ground
the plain ground that under this
mechanism it is clear that people have
most resources have an advantage and
that continue to say that that's their
been personally oh I've I've earned this
this is now my these are my resources
I've done it myself know what self-made
all of this is because we're all working
together so this needs to be a way to
make sure that we redouble the playing
ground periodically people to kind of
start fresh figure out what works now I
think that is very important um the idea
of a dead you bully it's funny everyone
keeps it's my name but no that's funny
of my whole life and why that's that
name it was from the Bible it's a time
period where they got all the slaves
free accounts of all that I think it was
every fifty years and how important that
is and at the same time a lot of what a
debt Jubilee does is prop up the middle
class not the lower call a because if if
you
don't have debt it doesn't help you
right it's not helping you get out of
poverty if you don't have dead it's not
something like what Remzi with common
planet suggests which is giving people
money right like having a universal
principle I'm having a way to distribute
or just by being a human being on this
planet you have you have access to to
some currency or unit of exchange I
think that is that is powerful and
needed because that undoes a lot of the
wrongs of the past unlike I think just a
deeply I'm like oh wait I don't look I
don't own my house do I get to live in
my house and keep it but someone with a
mortgage in Vancouver does like there's
a lot of still inequalities that we
still need to look at but I still would
be ok with that over what we currently
have which is basically how I feel about
all game be stuff it's like I would sign
up for it even if I see that there are
some some issues with it it's funny I
think that um it's important to
recognize that the comforter could be of
that you know whatever it's implement it
is going to be a challenge
and certainly warps any past sense of
debt right with education and housing
and and and corporate debt it is the
sense I mean in a way the problem right
now is that actually I think the biggest
aspect of why I see something going
towards game B is the degree to which we
externalise costs and don't really
account for them is the extent to which
the economy is an abstraction where the
what what we think of as as that part of
the economy doesn't really as much as it
needs to what the actual constraints are
in the world we're able to ignore those
so there's this there's a macro level
effect and then there's the micro level
effect what happens each one of us I
think there's a lot of complexity there
but I think the main thing is again it's
how do we deal with this in a feedback
we're gonna
it allows us to see really where are we
what's happening and I think that it has
to happen on a a very micro time scale
as well like what are the decisions that
you're making over the time and are you
or you know it's for instance if we do
something like a universal basic income
what's the impact of that as well if I
give you fifteen hundred also a month or
whatever and a year are you eating
healthy living healthy or are you just
playing video games all day I mean it's
kind of like not so much from a judge of
did that work but are you able to
actually engage in that and that in a
way that is promoting health or are you
are you degrading your your
circumstances also as this is referring
back to our last conversation David on
Monday is this hedonism that you kind of
need to go through I mean I think a lot
of what happens when you say they were
gonna give people University basic
universal basic income is people almost
need to go through a hedonistic stage of
leg yeah I play video games all day
every day and watch television for two
years and then it got really boring and
I figured out what I wanted to do and
who move forward in that and to let
people be in that space and so as an
individual you gauge whether or not you
feel like you're being fulfilled playing
video games all day it's not gonna
fulfill you unless it is right if you're
fighting other ways to get your social
needs and your your health needs met
right if we have ways of like okay if
you are addicted to video games that's
all you're doing how can we still help
you eat healthy how can we still like
meeting people where they're at by
continually asking like what would help
what would stop you from playing video
games all day what would stop you from
playing video games and then helping you
create that instead of just saying that
that's not right right that you're not
contributing enough to society because
you're playing video games it's about I
think a personal do you feel good
playing video games all day if not how
can we help you not and if you do then I
think you're actually helping the world
the best way you can by playing video
games all day I can I say something
about that I think that that that I
understand where you're coming from and
some people can get to that realization
that playing video games all day it's
not gonna work for them and they don't
feel fulfilled but then you also have to
you know sink into consideration like
addictions and mental illness and other
things that would contribute to someone
playing video games or using drugs or
doing anything that could be addictive
that fulfillment who would not play a
part of it because it's all in the mind
and so like I don't know how how would
that work in that in that sense as
someone who has addictions addictions or
you know mental illness and trauma and
have spent a large part of my life not
mean those things with media like video
games and with there's only so much I
could handle before I had to go inside
and be like this feels gross I'm still
in a very toxic world right and so in a
world that that's hurting me because of
the what I call capitalism like the fact
that there is so many people with
addiction so much inequality so much
suffering around me I was trying to numb
out I could deal with my own stuff as
much as I could but I couldn't deal with
the rest until I figured out what I
think is a solution and now I'm moving
towards that I found a purpose and that
although I still have my addictions it's
pulling me out of it while unconscious
with it it has to be my choice and it
has to be like where am i meeting myself
right what makes me feel good if I spend
all day watching watching TV in video
games that's okay but not what I do it
for months on end or weeks on end I
start feeling rose and the the rats in a
cage own experiment or they took rats
and gave them heroin and they overdose
because they had nothing and they put
them in heaven where they like had
social interaction and they had mazes
and all that stuff and it would still
maybe take the opioid they would never
overdose and it's often seen as either
like a mental issue for addiction or a
social failing instead of what we're
starting to see it as which is the cage
ages the problem and we're you and
that's where I think the hedonism when
you literally give people what they
think they want the castle or the the
video game yeah sure do it all day every
day
you're not like as long as you're still
able to meet your needs you still have
to participate
no one's gonna hand you food right
without you participating at all in the
unless maybe we're at the very depths of
your addiction and we're like right we
need to get you to get you through you
will starve to death in your addiction
right I never does that
that level of addiction I mean pot makes
you eat more not less so it's you know
it's it's that dealing with people where
they are and empowering them right what
would help you not smoke pot today what
could fill that void right what what
being with other rats right like being
with other people in a way that actually
works that isn't society's version of
like they'd go out to a coffee shop I
mean out to a coffee shop is torture for
me it's too loud too chaotic but sitting
with someone and having a real
conversation is amazing so that's coming
that online within my capacity that I
can I can do so so there's something
there's nothing really interesting in
the end I want to first to note that if
anybody's watching this because they're
interested in argument on Marxism become
communist this is not going to satisfy
really looking at a different a
different thing but I think it's an
important aspect and what you just said
about I also look at the one of the
conclusions from rats in a cage whether
they whether they see their addiction or
whether they live healthily right - so
in some extent if I if I play this out
and in my mind if I ask the rest in the
cage what it wants it's clear it wants
heroin cocaine right it wants to wants
to just to make the pain go away if it's
living in heaven what it wants us to
continue to do that it doesn't need
something that helps it cope with the
pain but and and and and it will do that
what we've seen is it'll do that until
death or until it hits rock bottom and
simply has an insight for people who
deal with addiction clear that's a
number of people who deal with
addictions mean that a lot of people
feel like they're living in a cage and
if we ask people what they want when
they're living in a cage its relief and
that is I just say go take care of this
on your own
the tendency to go to addictive behavior
until it's clear this addictive behavior
is never going to get me out of this
loop I'm only going to keep making the
cage it's gonna make the cage persist
and I'm not gonna be able to get out of
the cage the only way out of this cage
is to really back up and say okay I need
to do mine but that's a that's a really
interesting shift you know I think that
you almost this is part of what I mean
by the feedback loop we need to be able
to use rationality you know and I'm
using Vegas concept of that of a
feedback loop intelligence to say okay
at the beginning of the week if I just
do what I want by the end of the week I
think you will be here and then as you
mature okay I play video games and I
think of the week I'm gonna be happy
relaxed I'll be be free I'll finally
have the clarity of mind able to go out
and get a job or whatever or or be
filled and I guess it's like no I feel
miserable okay well let's try this again
I still feel miserable yeah well maybe
the hypothesis they're playing video
games for a week will make me happy is
faulty so how do we alter that
hypothesis and really try a new
experiment yeah absolutely and so we're
at we're past the 30-minute work so I'm
gonna give each of you an opportunity to
wrap up your thoughts and then we can
end the live portion and decide whether
what we want to do with this video okay
I think I think that was a good ending
point for me I don't think have anything
else to say and same here I think yeah
the same all right perfect thank you
very much for participating in the idea
cafe stop broadcast now bye YouTube